<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE ALGORITHM SYSTEM "https://cms.hivdb.org/prod/downloads/asi/ASI2.2.dtd">
<ALGORITHM>
  <ALGNAME>HIVDB-HIV2</ALGNAME>
  <ALGVERSION>9.0</ALGVERSION>
  <ALGDATE>2024-01-13</ALGDATE>
  <DEFINITIONS>
    <GENE_DEFINITION>
      <NAME>PR</NAME>
      <DRUGCLASSLIST>PI</DRUGCLASSLIST>
    </GENE_DEFINITION>
    <GENE_DEFINITION>
      <NAME>RT</NAME>
      <DRUGCLASSLIST>NRTI</DRUGCLASSLIST>
    </GENE_DEFINITION>
    <GENE_DEFINITION>
      <NAME>IN</NAME>
      <DRUGCLASSLIST>INSTI</DRUGCLASSLIST>
    </GENE_DEFINITION>
    <LEVEL_DEFINITION>
      <ORDER>1</ORDER>
      <ORIGINAL>Susceptible</ORIGINAL>
      <SIR>S</SIR>
    </LEVEL_DEFINITION>
    <LEVEL_DEFINITION>
      <ORDER>2</ORDER>
      <ORIGINAL>Potential Low-Level Resistance</ORIGINAL>
      <SIR>S</SIR>
    </LEVEL_DEFINITION>
    <LEVEL_DEFINITION>
      <ORDER>3</ORDER>
      <ORIGINAL>Low-Level Resistance</ORIGINAL>
      <SIR>I</SIR>
    </LEVEL_DEFINITION>
    <LEVEL_DEFINITION>
      <ORDER>4</ORDER>
      <ORIGINAL>Intermediate Resistance</ORIGINAL>
      <SIR>I</SIR>
    </LEVEL_DEFINITION>
    <LEVEL_DEFINITION>
      <ORDER>5</ORDER>
      <ORIGINAL>High-Level Resistance</ORIGINAL>
      <SIR>R</SIR>
    </LEVEL_DEFINITION>
    <DRUGCLASS>
      <NAME>NRTI</NAME>
      <DRUGLIST>ABC,AZT,D4T,DDI,FTC,3TC,TDF</DRUGLIST>
    </DRUGCLASS>
    <DRUGCLASS>
      <NAME>PI</NAME>
      <DRUGLIST>ATV/r,DRV/r,FPV/r,IDV/r,LPV/r,NFV,SQV/r,TPV/r</DRUGLIST>
    </DRUGCLASS>
    <DRUGCLASS>
      <NAME>INSTI</NAME>
      <DRUGLIST>BIC,DTG,EVG,RAL</DRUGLIST>
    </DRUGCLASS>
    <GLOBALRANGE><![CDATA[(-INF TO 9 => 1,  10 TO 14 => 2,  15 TO 29 => 3,  30 TO 59 => 4,  60 TO INF => 5)]]></GLOBALRANGE>
    <COMMENT_DEFINITIONS>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN46R">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K46R is an uncommon nonpolymorphic HIV-2-associated RAL-selected mutation that alone has a minimal effect on RAL or DTG susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN51Y">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[H51Y is an HIV-1-associated drug-resistance mutation which has not yet been reported in HIV-2 infected persons.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN66AIK">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T66AIK are HIV-1-associated drug-resistance mutations which have not been reported in HIV-2 infected patients.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN84V">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I84V is a common polymorphic HIV-2- associated mutation that occurs significantly more commonly in RAL-experienced compared with INSTI-naïve persons. It has a minimal effect on RAL or DTG susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN91R">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q91R is a nonpolymorphic HIV-2-associated RAL-selected mutation that alone has a minimal effect on RAL or DTG susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN92AGQ">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E92AQ are nonpolymorphic HIV-2 associated mutations selected by RAL while E92G has been selected in one person receiving DTG. Alone, they are associated with reduced EVG susceptibility. They contribute reduced susceptibility to each of the INSTIs when combined with other INSTI DRMs. ]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN97A">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T97A is a common nonpolymorphic INSTI-selected mutation. In combination with other DRMs, it contributes reduced susceptibility to RAL, EVG, and possibly DTG and BIC.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN118R">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G118R is an uncommon nonpolymorphtic HIV-2-associated mutation which has been reported in one person who received RAL followed by DTG.  It is associated with about 6-fold reduced RAL susceptibility and about 8-fold reduced DTG susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN119T">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[A119T is a polymorphic HIV-2-associated mutation which occurs significantly more commonly in RAL-experienced compared with INSTI-naïve persons. Alone it has a minimal effect on INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN121Y">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F121Y is an uncommon nonpolymorphic HIV-1-associated drug-resistance mutation which has not been reported in HIV-2 infected patients.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN140SA">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G140SA are common nonpolymorphic HIV-2 associated drug-resistance mutations that usually occur in combination with Q148 mutations. Alone, they have little effect on INSTI susceptibility but in combination with mutations at position 148, they are associated with high level reductions in susceptibility to RAL and DTG.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN141I">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V141I is a slightly polymorphic mutation that is selected by RAL and possibly DTG. It usually occurs in combination with other INSTI-selected mutations. By itselft, it has a minimal effect on RAL and DTG susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN143CRGH">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y143CRGH are non-polymorphic HIV-2 mutations that have been reported in persons receiving RAL and that reduce RAL susceptibility. In combination with other mutations, they may also reduce susceptibility to EVG.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN147G">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[S147G is a nonpolymorphic HIV-1-associated drug-resistance mutation that has been reported in one RAL-treated HIV-2-infected person. Its effects on INSTI susceptibility for HIV-2 have not been reported.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN148HKR">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q148HKR are nonpolymorphic HIV-2 associated drug-resistance mutations, which reduce susceptibility to each of the INSTIs. They usually occur in combination with mutations at position 140 or 138 which with Q148 mutations lead to high level reductions in susceptibility to each of the INSTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN153SG">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[A153G is a nonpolymorphic HIV-2 mutation that is selected by RAL usually in combination with N155H. In combination with N155H, it is associated with about 2-fold reduced susceptibility to DTG and 15-fold reduced susceptibility to RAL. A153S is a polymorphic RAL-selected mutation which reduces INSTI susceptibility less than A153G.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN155H">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N155H is a nonpolymorphic HIV-2 associated drug-resistance mutation which reduces susceptibility to RAL and EVG. Alone it causes low-level reduced susceptibility to DTG. Higher level reductions in DTG susceptibility can occur in combination with additional mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN231_">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Among HIV-2 isolates, amino acid insertions at position 231 have been selected by RAL. They are ass and associated with markedly reduced susceptibility to each of the INSTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2AIN263K">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[R263K is a nonpolymorphic HIV-1-associated drug-resistance mutation which has so far been rarely reported in HIV-2 infected persons. By itself, it apperars to have a minimal effect on susceptibility to RAL and DTG.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR10I">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V10I is a minimally polymorphic mutation that occurs significantly more commonly in PI-treated than PI-naïve HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR23I">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L23I is an uncommon non-polymorphic HIV-1 associated PI-resistance mutation that has not been reported in HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR30N">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[D30N is a non-polymorphic mutation that causes high-level HIV-1 resistance to NFV. It has rarely been reported in HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR33I">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V33I is a minimally polymorphic mutation that occurs significantly more commonly in PI-treated than PI-naïve HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR45R">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K45R is a minimally polymorphic mutation that occurs significantly more commonly in PI-treated than PI-naïve HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR47A">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V47A is a common non-polymorphic PI-selected HIV-2 mutation that reduces HIV-2 susceptibility to LPV and other PIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR48VA">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G48VA are non-polymorphic PI-selected HIV-2 mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR50L">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I50L is a non-polymorphic HIV-2 mutation selected by ATV. It causes high-level resistance to ATV and increases susceptibility to most of the remaining PIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR50V">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I50V is a non-polymorphic PI-selected mutation that reduces HIV-2 susceptibility to LPV and other PIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR53LY">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F53LY are nonpolymorphic mutations that have rarely been reported in treated HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR54L">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I54L is a nonpolymorphic PI-selected mutation.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR54M">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I54M is a very common non-polymorphic PI-selected mutation. It is associated with reduced HIV-2 susceptibility to multiple Pis.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR56V">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T56V is a common nonpolymrophic mutation that occurs significantly more commonly in HIV-2 isolates from PI-treated vs. PI-naïve isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR62A">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V62A is a nonpolymorphic mutation that occurs significantly more commonly in PI-treated than PI-naïve HIV-2 isolates. It has been selected in vitro by IDV and been shown to contribute reduced suscptibility to LPV in combination with other DRMs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR64V">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I64V is a polymorphic mutation that occurs singnificatnly more commonly in PI-treated than PI-naïve HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR71I">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V71I is a common polymorphic mutation that occurs significantly more commonly in PI-treated than PI-naïve HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR73G">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[A73G is a nonpolymorphic mutation that occurs significantly more commonly in PI-treated than PI-naïve HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR82F">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I82F is a common non-polymorphic PI-selected HIV-2 mutation that reduces HIV-2 susceptibility to LPV and other PIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR82LM">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I82LM are nonpolymorphic PI-selected HIV-2 mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR84V">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I84V is a non-polymorphic PI-selected HIV-2 mutation associated with reduced susceptibility to multiple Pis.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR85L">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F85L is a non-polymorphic PI-selected HIV-2 mutation.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR88D">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N88D is a nonpolymorphic HIV-1-associated PI resistance mutation that has rarely been reported in HIV-2 isolatea.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR90M">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L90M is a non-polymorphic PI-selected HIV-2 mutation.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2APR99F">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L99F is a polymorphic HIV-2 mutation that occurs significantly more commonly in PI-treated than PI-naïve persons. It has been selected in vitro by IDV and been shown to contribute reduced suscptibility to LPV in combination with other DRMs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART40R">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K40R is a nonpolymorphic mutation that occurs significantly more commonly in HIV-2 sequences from NRTI-treated than NRTI-naïve persons. It usually occurs in combination with S215YF mutations. Its effect on HIV-2 NRTI susceptibility is not known.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART41L">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M41L is an HIV-1 drug resistance mutation that has not been reported in NRTI-treated HIV-2-infected persons and has not been associated with reduced HIV-2 NRTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART62V">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[A62V is a common nonpolymoprhic HIV-2 associated mutation that usually occurs in combination with K65R.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART65RN">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K65R is a common HIV-2 drug-resistance mutation that is associated with reduced susceptibility to each of the NRTIs except possibly AZT. K65N is a rare HIV-2 drug-resistance mutation.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART67NGESTH">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[D67 mutations are commonly occurring HIV-1-assocateddrug-resistance mutations that are rarely selected in HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART69ST">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N69ST are polymorphic HIV-2 mutations that occurs with increased frequency in NRTI-treated persons. Their effects on HIV-2 NRTI susceptibility are not known.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART69_">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Insertions in the Beta3-Beta4 loop are associated with reduced HIV-1 susceptibility to each of the NRTIs but have not been reported in HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART69-">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Deletions in the Beta3-Beta4 loop are associated with reduced HIV-1 susceptibility to each of the NRTIs but have not been reported in HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART70RNSQT">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K70RNSQT are nonpolymorphic HIV-2 drug-resistance mutations that occur more commonly in sequences from NRTI-treated than NRTI-naïve persons. Their effects on HIV-2 susceptibility to NRTIs are not known.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART74VI">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L74VI are common HIV-1-associated NRTI-resistance mutations that have rarely been reported in HIV-2 sequences.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART75V">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I75V occurs significantly more commonly in HIV-2 sequences from NRTI-treated than NRTI-naïve persons but its effect on HIV-2 susceptibility to NRTIs is uncertain.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART77L">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F77L is an accessory HIV-1-associated mutation that usually occurs in combination with the multi-NRTI resistance mutation Q151M. It has not been associated with NRTI therapy in HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART111I">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V111I is a common polymorphic mutation that occurs significantly more commonly in HIV-2 sequences from NRTI-treated than NRTI-naïve persons. It appears to increase the replication fitness of HIV-2 variants containing other HIV-2-associated NRTI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART115F">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y115F is a common nonpolymorphic HIV-2-drug-resistance mutation that usually occurs in combination with other other NRTI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART116Y">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F116Y is an accessory HIV-1-associated mutation that usually occurs in combination with the multi-NRTI resistance mutation Q151M. It has not been associated with NRTI therapy in HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART151M">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q151M is a common nonpolymorphic HIV-2 drug-resistance mutation thatcauses high-level resistance to each of the NRTIs except possibly TDF/TAF and 3TC/FTC.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART184VI">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M184V/I is the most common HIV-2 drug-resistance mutation. It causes high-level resistance to 3TC and FTC.  As is the case for HIV-1, it is likely that M184VI are not contraindications to continued treatment with 3TC or FTC because they increase susceptibility to TDF and are associated with clinically significant reductions in HIV-1 replication.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART210ACDEFGHIKLMPQRSTVWY_-">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[210W is an HIV-1 associated TAM. The HIV-2 consensus at this position is N. Mutations at this position have not been selected by NRTIs in HIV-2 isolates.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART214L">
        <!--<DATE>2020-05-04</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F214L is a slighly polymorphic HIV-2 mutation that occurs with increased frequency in NRTI-treated persons.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART215YF">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[S215YF are nonpolymorphic HIV-2 drug-resistance mutations that are selected by AZT.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART219-">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E219D is a polymorphic mutation that also appears to be selected by AZT.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="HIV2ART223R">
        <!--<DATE>2024-01-13</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K223R is a polymorphic HIV-2 mutation that occurs more commonly in NRTI-treated persons. It is considered to be associated with reduced AZT susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
    </COMMENT_DEFINITIONS>
  </DEFINITIONS>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>ABC</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>abacavir</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>AZT</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>zidovudine</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>D4T</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>stavudine</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>DDI</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>didanosine</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>FTC</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>emtricitabine</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>3TC</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>lamivudine</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>TDF</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>tenofovir</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>ATV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>atazanavir/r</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>DRV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>darunavir/r</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>FPV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>fosamprenavir/r</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>IDV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>indinavir/r</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>LPV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>lopinavir/r</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>NFV</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>nelfinavir</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>SQV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>saquinavir/r</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>TPV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>tipranavir/r</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>BIC</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>bictegravir</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>DTG</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>dolutegravir</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>EVG</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>elvitegravir</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>RAL</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>raltegravir</FULLNAME>
  </DRUG>
  <MUTATION_COMMENTS>
    <GENE>
      <NAME>IN</NAME>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>46R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN46R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>51Y</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN51Y"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>66AIK</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN66AIK"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>84V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN84V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>91R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN91R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>92AGQ</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN92AGQ"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>97A</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN97A"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>118R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN118R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>119T</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN119T"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>121Y</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN121Y"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>140SA</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN140SA"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>141I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN141I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>143CRGH</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN143CRGH"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>147G</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN147G"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>148HKR</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN148HKR"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>153SG</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN153SG"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>155H</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN155H"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>231i</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN231_"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>263K</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2AIN263K"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
    </GENE>
    <GENE>
      <NAME>PR</NAME>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>10I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR10I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>23I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR23I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>30N</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR30N"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>33I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR33I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>45R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR45R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>47A</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR47A"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>48VA</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR48VA"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>50L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR50L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>50V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR50V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>53LY</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR53LY"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>54L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR54L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>54M</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR54M"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>56V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR56V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>62A</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR62A"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>64V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR64V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>71I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR71I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>73G</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR73G"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>82F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR82F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>82LM</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR82LM"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>84V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR84V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>85L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR85L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>88D</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR88D"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>90M</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR90M"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>99F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2APR99F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
    </GENE>
    <GENE>
      <NAME>RT</NAME>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>40R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART40R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>41L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART41L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>62V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART62V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>65RN</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART65RN"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>67NGESTH</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART67NGESTH"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>69ST</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART69ST"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>69i</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART69_"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>69d</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART69-"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>70RNSQT</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART70RNSQT"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>74VI</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART74VI"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>75V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART75V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>77L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART77L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>111I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART111I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>115F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART115F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>116Y</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART116Y"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>151M</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART151M"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>184VI</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART184VI"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>210ACDEFGHIKLMPQRSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART210ACDEFGHIKLMPQRSTVWY_-"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>214L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART214L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>215YF</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART215YF"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>219d</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART219-"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>223R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="HIV2ART223R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
    </GENE>
  </MUTATION_COMMENTS>
  <RESULT_COMMENTS/>
</ALGORITHM>
